Guide to the Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932- AIS.1998.30.15
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Dick Thornburgh Papers, Series XV. Under-Secretary-General of the United Nations
1992-1993
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Thornburgh, Dick
AIS.1998.30.15
23.75 Linear Feet
Dick Thornburgh had rejoined Kirkpatrick and Lockhart following his unsuccessful campaign for U.S. Senate. When President Bush called on February 3, 1992, asking him to serve as Under-Secretary-General for Administration at the United Nations, he agreed to stay for a year, as a point person on reform. A year later, February 26, 1993, Thornburgh's so-called "Thornburgh Report" was delivered to the Secretary-General, a major component of which was creation of an inspector general position to address fraud and abuse. Included here are documents about the United Nations, its budget processes, peacekeeping efforts, administrative organization, and economic and social development programs. Thornburgh made four trips abroad and each is well documented. Of particular note is the trip to the Vatican Conference on Religion and Disability in 1992. Regarding Thornburgh's final report, there are drafts and background material for all issues, as well as the final report itself that outlines both problems and suggested solutions. The files are in the following nine sections: Speeches; Under-Secretary-General Thornburgh's Files; Memoranda and Correspondence; Financial Restructuring and Peacekeeping; Events and Schedules; Foreign Trips; News Clippings; Country Files; and ongoing UN materials. Digital reproductions of portions of the collection are available online.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Dick Thornburgh, February 27, 1998.
Previous Citation
Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932-, AIS.1998.30, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Personal papers; Government; Politics; Associations; Rule of law; United Nations Convention against Illicit Traffic in Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances (1988); United Nations -- Reform; World Committee on Disability; United Nations. Under-Secretary-General for Administration and Management; Kirkpatrick & Lockhart; Thornburgh, Ginny (Judson); Thornburgh, Dick
- Under-Secretary-General of the United Nations, 1992-1993; XV.
  Scope and Contents note
  Having resigned as Attorney General of the United States to run, unsuccessfully, for the U.S. Senate seat left vacant by the tragic death of Senator John Heinz, Thornburgh was again at a career turning point. He had rejoined Kirkpatrick and Lockhart, his law firm over the years, but was surprised once again by a call from President Bush, on 9:30 Monday morning, February 3, 1992. The President said "we need some help at the United Nations ... and [Thornburgh], as a longtime supporter of the UN, knew immediately that this was yet another 'offer [he] couldn't refuse' " (Evidence, p. 316).
  Thornburgh became Under-Secretary-General for Administration at the United Nations, and agreed to stay for a year, as a point person on reform. The organization was seen as mismanaged, resistant to reform and change, and the prognosis for it was not very optimistic. The Washington Post reported that "UN sources say that if Thornburgh takes the job, [Secretary-General] Boutros-Ghali will gain three big advantages. He will have the weight of the world's only remaining super power directly behind the reform effort; he will be giving the United States a chance to show that ideas about reform are workable; and he will have a deputy who stands a better chance than anyone else at the United Nations of making the United States pay its arrears" (Evidence, p. 318).
  A year later, on Friday, February 26, Thornburgh's last day on the job, his detailed report was delivered to the Secretary-General. Outside of the UN what became known as the Thornburgh Report was generally well received and his efforts did not go unnoticed. The National Journal's assessment two years after his departure from the UN stated: "The impetus for administrative and fiscal reforms at the United Nations can be credited in large part to intense prodding during the Reagan and Bush administrations. Many of today's cost-cutting stratagems, including the creation of a quasi-inspector general's post to ferret out fraud and waste, stem from a management review conducted by President Bush's Attorney General Dick Thornburgh" (Evidence, p. 332).
  As Thornburgh reflected: "At the end of February 1993, I left New York and headed back to Washington, my twenty-five-year career in public office at an end. I looked forward to resuming life under one roof with my beloved Ginny. And after over two decades of the pressure cooker environment of public responsibility, I was ready for a transition to the role of 'useful citizen' " (Evidence, p. 334). His extensive, and very useful, continuing activities are well represented in the collection section entitled "Ongoing Career."
  Included here are numerous documents about the United Nations, its budget processes, peacekeeping efforts, administrative organization, and economic and social development programs. Thornburgh made four trips abroad in the course of carrying out his responsibilities and each is well documented here. Of particular note is the trip to Rome, to the Vatican Conference on Religion and Disability, in 1992. Regarding Thornburgh's final report, there are drafts and background material for all issues, as well as the final report itself. Having spent the year identifying what was wrong with the UN, the report outlined some ways to fix the problems, such as: restructuring and redeployment, cutting waste in publications, a moratorium on costly worldwide conferences, personnel changes, more attention to peacekeeping budgets, a twenty-four hour communications center and funding of an outside management study. "The final section of the report focused on fraud, waste and abuse ... urged the creation of a new Office of Inspector General and changes to accounting systems ... to compel full financial disclosure by senior management ... and expedited treatment of allegations of wrongdoing" (Evidence, p. 331).
  The files are presented in the following nine sections: Speeches; Under-Secretary-General Thornburgh's Files; Memoranda and Correspondence; Financial Restructuring and Peacekeeping; Events and Schedules; Foreign Trips; News Clippings; Country Files; Ongoing UN materials, 1993-2000.
  - Speeches and Testimony, 1.
    The twelve speeches from Thornburgh's year as Under-Secretary-General of the United Nations (UN) all are available here online. The files of speeches are arranged chronologically. Topics include for example: white collar crime, disabilities, budgetary issues of the UN, and peacekeeping problems of administration and finance.
    - "The Internalization of White Collar Crime," White Collar Crime National Institute, 1992 Conference, San Francisco, CA, March 6, 1992 (Box 960, Folder 1)
    - Opening Session of the Eastern European Conference on Disabilities, Prague, Czech and Slovak Federal Republic, April 13, 1992 (Box 960, Folder 2)
    - Advisory Committee on Administrative and Budgetary Questions, New York, NY, April 16, 1992 (Box 960, Folder 3)
    - Advisory Committee on Administrative and Budgetary Questions, New York, NY, May 6, 1992 (Box 960, Folder 4)
    - Statement to the Sixteenth Session of the Staff Management Coordinating Committee, New York, NY, June 16, 1992 (Box 960, Folder 5)
    - Remarks upon Accepting the Distinguished Service Medal of the American Legion, Chicago, IL, August 26, 1992 (Box 960, Folder 6)
    - Statement to the Committee for Programme and Coordination (CPC), New York, NY, August 31, 1992 (Box 960, Folder 7)
    - Statement before the Advisory Committee on Administrative and Budgetary Questions, New York, NY, September 16, 1992 (Box 960, Folder 8)
    - Statement before the International Conference of Ministers Responsible for the Status of Persons with Disabilities, Montreal, Quebec, Canada, October 8, 1992 (Box 960, Folder 9)
    - Statement before the Fifth Committee of the General Assembly, New York, NY, October 13, 1992 (Box 960, Folder 10)
    - "Peace-keeping: Problems of Administration and Finance," remarks by Dick Thornburgh to a Symposium sponsored by the Yale Center for International and Area Studies, New Haven, CT, October 31, 1992 (Box 960, Folder 11)
    - "The Disabled and the Law Throughout the World," An address to the Seventh International Conference of the Pontifical Council for Pastoral Assistance to Health Care Workers, The Vatican, Rome, Italy, November 20, 1992 (Box 960, Folder 12)
  - Under-Secretary-General Thornburgh's Files, 2.
    During his year at the United Nations (UN), Thornburgh accumulated files, much like those elsewhere in this collection, that were kept at hand for convenient reference. Their usefulness is evidenced by Thornburgh's heavy annotations, and personal notes, on entire notepad sheets or even on tiny paper scraps. The materials relate to the potential restructuring of the UN from the perspective of the Department of Administration and Management (DAM), which Thornburgh headed as Under-Secretary-General (USG). These files represent a work-in-progress that will be insightful.
    An issue of particular significance to Thornburgh was the potential of a new Office of Inspector General within the UN, to address issues of fraud, waste and abuse. The background of this matter is well documented. Other background on the UN includes speeches and op-eds by Secretary-General Boutros Boutros-Ghali, UN news releases, Thornburgh notes, and "checklists" regarding peacekeeping. Also prominent in the files are some of his writings and articles while USG, and news releases about his work. Thornburgh's final report to the Secretary-General (dated March 1, 1993), subsequently known as the "Thornburgh Report," is included, with background material and drafts.
    The arrangement of "Thornburgh's files" is an alphabetical listing of topics and/or departmental issues. Thornburgh's speeches, the final report, and a transcript of an interview with him are all available here online. Also online is a list of UN abbreviations, which surely will assist any researcher using these files.
    - Department of Administration and Management (DAM), Office of Conference Services (OCS): Thornburgh's notes, restructuring plans and memoranda, February-December, 1992 (Box 960, Folder 13)
    - Department of Administration and Management (DAM): general materials regarding department organization, March-June, 1992 (Box 960, Folder 14)
    - Department of Administration and Management (DAM), Office of General Services: Thornburgh's notes and briefing material, 1992-1993 (Box 960, Folder 15)
    - Department of Administration and Management (DAM), Office of Human Resources Management: personnel issues, February-November, 1992 (Box 960, Folder 16)
    - Department of Administration and Management (DAM), Internal Audit Division (IAD): Thornburgh's notes and IAD work plan, March, 1992 (Box 960, Folder 17)
    - Department of Administration and Management (DAM), Joint Advisory Committee (JAC): Thornburgh's notes, meetings and memoranda, March-September, 1992 (Box 960, Folder 18)
    - Department of Administration and Management (DAM), Joint Appeals Board (JAB): regarding appeal procedures, April, 1992 (Box 960, Folder 19)
    - Department of Administration and Management (DAM), Office of Programme, Planning, Budget and Finance (OPPBF): Thornburgh's notes, February-September, 1992 (Box 960, Folder 20)
    - Department of Administration and Management (DAM): Restructuring materials and memoranda on "six month plans", April-June, 1992 (Box 960, Folder 21)
    - Department of Administration and Management (DAM): "Six month plan of action", April-June, 1992 (Box 960, Folder 22)
    - Department of Administration and Management (DAM): Thornburgh's weekly meeting notes, March, 1992-February, 1993 (Box 960, Folder 23)
    - Department of Administration and Management (DAM): Thornburgh's notes (Linda Cohen meeting), September 10, 1992 (Box 960, Folder 24)
    - Department of Administration and Management (DAM): United Nations Staff Union and Coordinating Committee for Independent Staff Unions and Associations (CCISUA), February-May, 1992 (Box 960, Folder 25)
    - Biographies of United Nations staff members, March-June, 1992 (Box 960, Folder 26)
    - Briefing material on United Nations, prepared for Thornburgh, February 13, 1992 (Box 960, Folder 27-28)
    - Thornburgh's notes from briefing material on United Nations, February 13, 1992 (Box 960, Folder 29)
    - Career Development System for the United Nations Secretariat: reports, drafts and notes, May-August, 1992 (Box 960, Folder 30)
    - Christine Rollet memoranda and correspondence regarding restructuring, 1992-1993 (Box 960, Folder 31)
    - Congratulations and thank you cards, February, 1992-February, 1993 (Box 961, Folder 1)
    - Cuyler Walker's notes regarding Thornburgh at the United Nations, February 27, 1992-November 23, 1992 (Box 961, Folder 2-4)
    - Fifth Committee of the United Nations General Assembly: notes, agendas and reports, September, 1992 (Box 961, Folder 5)
    - Geneva Group meeting: Thornburgh's notes, September 29, 1992 (Box 961, Folder 6)
    - Group of Ten: requests and objectives, March, 1992 (Box 961, Folder 7)
    - Office of Inspector General: Creation of office to strengthen UN audit capabilities, 1992-1993 (Box 961, Folder 8-10)
    - Office of Inspector General: UN Auditing reports and the position of the United States, 1991-1992 (Box 961, Folder 11)
    - Office of Inspector General: United Nations Code of Conduct for staff members, including handling and reporting finances, 1986-1993 (Box 961, Folder 12)
    - International Civil Service Commission (ICSC): report and statement by the Secretary General (SG), March-November, 1992 (Box 961, Folder 13)
    - Jean Claude Aime, Thornburgh's notes regarding, 1992-1993 (Box 961, Folder 14)
    - Memorabilia (including handwritten notes dated 3.10.92 "Re: S-G" outlining job and goals), 1992 (Box 961, Folder 15)
    - Permanent Missions to the United Nations No. 271, UN publication, September, 1992 (Box 961, Folder 16)
    - Secretary-General Boutros-Ghali: Reports, clippings, memoranda, 1991-1993 (Box 961, Folder 17)
    - Secretary-General Boutros-Ghali: Thornburgh's meeting notes, March-November, 1992 (Box 961, Folder 18)
    - Security and safety service activities reports, 1987-1991 (Box 962, Folder 1)
    - Speeches, and drafts, 1992-1993 (Box 962, Folder 2)
      - Statement by Dick Thornburgh to the Committee for Programme and Coordination, New York, NY, May 11, 1992; 1.
      - Statement by Dick Thornburgh before the Joint Appeals Board (JAB) annual meeting, New York, NY, June 8, 1992; 2.
      - Address by Dick Thornburgh to the Overseas Press Club, New York, NY, January 28, 1993; 3.
      - Notes prepared for a speech by Dick Thornburgh to the World Affairs Council, Pittsburgh, PA, January 29, 1993; 4.
    - Stationery samples, [ca. 1992] (Box 962, Folder 3)
    - Thornburgh's notes, to-do lists, United Nations information and contacts, 1992-1993 (Box 962, Folder 4)
    - Thornburgh's notes regarding the United Nations, 1992-1993 (Box 962, Folder 5)
    - Thornburgh's notes and background materials on UNICEF, July 1, 1992 (Box 962, Folder 6)
    - Transcript of Hans Janitschek's interview with Thornburgh for UN Staff Report, March 31, 1992 (Box 962, Folder 7)
    - United Nations Association (UNA), March, 1992 (Box 962, Folder 8)
    - United Nations background: abbreviation list, undated (Box 962, Folder 9)
    - United Nations background: "Charter of the United Nations and Statute of the International Court of Justice", April, 1989 (Box 962, Folder 10)
    - United Nations background: news releases, 1992-1994 (Box 962, Folder 11)
    - United Nations background: notes of Thornburgh and early materials, February, 1992 (Box 962, Folder 12)
    - United Nations background: the United Nations at 40 years old and 50 years old, 1985, 1995 (Box 962, Folder 13)
    - United Nations background: the organization of the UN Secretariat, February 28, 1992 (Box 962, Folder 14)
    - United Nations background: Speeches and op-eds by Boutros Boutros-Ghali, Secretary-General (SG) of the United Nations, 1992-1996 (Box 962, Folder 15)
    - United Nations "checklists" regarding peace-keeping, United Nations Development Programme (UNDP) and relations with the United States, February-October, 1992 (Box 962, Folder 16)
    - United Nations news releases regarding Thornburgh, February, 1992 (Box 962, Folder 17)
      - Former U.S. Attorney General and Pennsylvania Governor Dick Thornburgh issued statement on his appointment as United Nations Undersecretary General for Administration and Management, February 13, 1992; 1.
      - United Nations news release regarding Thornburgh's appointment as Under-Secretary-General of the UN, February 14, 1992; 2.
      - Plan to create three new departments in economic and social field introduced in Fifth Committee: Concerns raised on Assembly's Role in Restructuring Decision Making, December 9, 1992; 3.
    - "A Concept Paper: Restructuring of UN Economic and Social Programmes" and unpublished article, October 21, 1992 (Box 962, Folder 18)
    - "Time for Real Reform in the United Nations," article and drafts by Thornburgh, 1992-1993 (Box 962, Folder 19)
    - "Needed: A United Nations Inspector General," article and drafts by Thornburgh, 1992-1993 (Box 962, Folder 20)
    - "Today's United Nations in a Changing World," article and drafts by Thornburgh, 1992-1993 (Box 962, Folder 21)
    - "The Missing Piece: A Balanced Budget Amendment," article by Thornburgh, [ca. 1992] (Box 962, Folder 22)
    - Report to the Secretary-General of the United Nations by Dick Thornburgh, Under-Secretary General for Administration and Management, March 1, 1993 (Box 962, Folder 23)
    - Report to the Secretary-General (SG) of the United Nations (UN) by Dick Thornburgh, drafts and notes, March 1, 1993 (Box 962, Folder 24)
    - Background material for papers and reports, 1992-1993 (Box 962, Folder 25)
  - Memoranda and Correspondence, 3.
    This section of material contains all major correspondence written to and from Thornburgh during his year as Under-Secretary-General for Administration and Management. In addition, there is a large section of memoranda both to and from Thornburgh, most regarding financial restructuring, including the "six month plan[s] of action," which would state the goals and the plans of each department and office to "clean up their financial act."
    Of particular interest in these files are two letters written to Thornburgh, each having to do with Thornburgh's final report to the Secretary General, from Presidents Clinton and Bush. Both of these letters commend Thornburgh for his work in the UN and his tireless efforts as a public servant.
    - Inter-office memoranda to Thornburgh, 1991-1993 (Box 963, Folder 1-3)
    - Inter-office memoranda from Thornburgh, 1993 (Box 963, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, from Thornburgh (includes resignation letter to Secretary General Boutros Boutros-Ghali), 1992-1993 (Box 963, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, to Thornburgh, alpha: A-Z, 1992-1993 (Box 963, Folder 6-8)
    - Correspondence, to and from Thornburgh, chron, March, 1992-February, 1993 (Box 964, Folder 1-11)
    - Personal correspondence, 1992-1993 (Box 964, Folder 12-13)
    - Correspondence regarding Thornburgh's report to the Secretary General, dated March 1, 1993, March-November, 1993 (Box 964, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence regarding Thornburgh's report to the Secretary General: Letter from President Bill Clinton to Thornburgh, includes original, September 23, 1993 (Box 964, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence regarding Thornburgh's report to the Secretary General: Letter from President George Bush to Thornburgh, original copy, [ca. 1993] (Box 964, Folder 16)
  - Financial Restructuring and Peacekeeping, 4.
    The files here relate to the processes of restructuring of UN economic and social programs, of reorganizing the departments, of elimination of duplication and overlap, and include, for example, materials from the Ford Foundation regarding financing planning for the UN. Thornburgh also received a wealth of reports on different paths to economic reorganization and conducted "follow-ups," or updates on different branches of the UN, including the ECLAC, UNOV and UNOG, ECOSOC, UNCED and others, which are included here.
    Thornburgh's work at the UN also involved reforming the budget process, which he writes was "'almost surreal' in its complexity and in the degree to which it entailed the rigorous review and micromanagement of minutiae" (Evidence, p.323). Regular budget contributions had to be considered separately from those of peacekeeping, which had its own assessment formula for member states. Thus, to Thornburgh, peacekeeping was integrally related to finances and his financial restructuring task. A major concern, for example, was that member states were lax on paying their peacekeeping dues. He writes, "Only about one-third of peacekeeping duties were being paid within the first three months of a mission, so much interaccount borrowing and fancy financial footwork was required even to provide bare necessities. I was to compare this process later to a financial 'bungee jump': missions were undertaken in hope and faith, but with no assurance, that they would eventually be funded" (Evidence, p.325).
    Thus, the materials in this section are divided into two groups: 1) Financial restructuring of UN Departments, arranged chronologically, including economic concerns, budget problems and proposals; 2) Financial restructuring of UN with considerations to UN peacekeeping efforts, arranged chronologically, including the tracking of peacekeeping finances and the possibilities for reform to enable a more consistent funding in the future. Much of the material here includes handwritten notes and annotated material. Many of the reports include Thornburgh's red pen annotations.
    - Financial Restructuring of UN Departments
      - "Review of the Efficiency of the Administrative and Financial Functioning of the United Nations," a report of the Secretary-General (SG) to the General Assembly, December, 1990 (Box 965, Folder 1)
      - "Report to the Secretary-General (SG) on the Review of the Planning and Management of Peacekeeping Operations and Other Special Missions," submitted by the Independent Team Appointed Pursuant to Secretary General's Bulletin of July 23, 1991, September 6, 1991 (Box 965, Folder 2)
      - Updates and "follow-ups" on United Nations Office in Vienna (UNOV), 1991-1992 (Box 965, Folder 3)
      - Department of Peacekeeping Operations, USG Marrack Goulding, tasks and staffing, February-June, 1992 (Box 965, Folder 4)
      - Integrated Management Information System project (IMIS), restructuring workflows, February-July, 1992 (Box 965, Folder 5)
      - First phase of restructuring reviewed and adopted by the 46th General Assembly, February-July, 1992 (Box 965, Folder 6)
      - Internal memoranda regarding restructuring, March, 1992-February, 1993 (Box 965, Folder 7)
      - Material on the UN financial situation, including information regarding contributions and budget, April-May, 1992 (Box 965, Folder 8)
      - Updates and "follow-ups" on United Nations Office in Geneva (UNOG), April-July, 1992 (Box 965, Folder 9)
      - Updates and "follow-ups" for UN High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR), April-July, 1992 (Box 965, Folder 10)
      - Reform of UN Governance and Finance and final report by the Nordic UN Project, May-June, 1992 (Box 965, Folder 11)